So for this exercise, what I'd like you to do is also get some hands-on
experience just like you did with ViewRouter.
Go ahead and open up the Pinya docs for reference, because once again,
the docs are a great resource for helping to debug and learn more things
about the library as you continue using it.
Then go ahead and install Pinya onto the SailorView app and
configure View to use it.
Again, it should feel familiar based on what we just did with ViewRouter.
Go ahead and then create a stores folder, and then go ahead and
just create any kind of data store that you think makes sense for SailorView.
Then once you create your first store, try to add some state,
getters, or actions.
And then finally, go ahead and call those things inside of your components.
All right, so as always, if you have questions for those watching online,
please feel free to drop that in the chat.
Let's go ahead and run through that.
So, what we're going to do this is let's go ahead and restart.
And this time, we're going to go ahead to the SailorView, and
then we're going to install Pinya.
That's the first thing we're going to do.
Once we have that, then I can go ahead and run dev.
I'm going to have that over here, which is great.
Okay, that's working now.
So, once you have Pinya installed, what you got to do is you got to configure it.
So, inside of, oops, I'm in the wrong folder.
Inside of SailorView, for main.js, we have here,
this is where we're creating the ViewRouter.
Let's then go ahead and find CreatePinyaApp functionality from Pinya.
So, once again, verify that.
You can always check the autocomplete.
I usually do autocomplete because it just prevents the one off typing errors that
which you've seen me do on this workshop.
So, once we have that, great.
We can then, okay, we have a bunch of router stuff here.
Let me just collapse that.
And then const Pinya equals createPinya.
And what are we going to do?
App.usePinya.
All right, so, now that we have that enabled, we can go ahead and create our first store.
So, what we're going to do here, inside of our components, it looks like,
honestly, the user store makes the most sense.
So, we can go ahead and do userstore.js.
And so, we're going to go ahead and import definePinya from Pinya.
And then, we're going to export our store, which is going to be a const of useUserStore.
And we'll call the define, not definePinya, my mistake, defineStore.
We've already defined Pinya at the app level.
Now, we're defining a specific store.
The store gets what?
It gets two arguments.
One, what are we going to call the store?
Again, keep it simple.
I like to keep it whatever the file name is.
So, it's userstore.
And then, we get an option of what?
We get the state, which is a function that returns an object.
We get the getters.
And we have the actions.
Okay, so what we can do, if we take a look at our code, is inside of our views,
inside of user page, you can see that we're doing quite a bit here as far as the data goes.
Now, we're importing it currently from Composables.
Let's migrate that over.
That's what we're going to do in this particular one.
So, inside of Composables, you'll see that user list is just a ref.
Well, if that's the case, all we got to do here is to show you side-by-side.
In our user store, it's add a user list, and then just make it an array.
And when we save that, now, when we go inside of our user page,
rather than importing the user list like this, what we're going to do is we're going to
import the use user store from, and then this should be from stores slash user store,
just like that.
And so, again, let's just double-check.
I did get the right one.
Wait, nope.
Export cons use user store.
That should be the right one.
We'll find out just momentarily.
Okay, so then we will set up the store by what?
By calling our function.
So, cons user store equals use user store.
And then we'll go ahead and save that, and that looks good.
Okay, good.
Now, it's actually being fetched correctly.
That's good.
So, now that we have the user store, we can get rid of this dot value.
No longer that, it's just user store dot user list, just like that.
So, let's see if that actually worked.
We refresh, go to the user page, we'll see something is not working.
Okay, why?
Because, guess what?
We're looking at user store dot user list, but inside of our template,
you'll see that we're only referring to user list directly.
So, again, one of the things I like about the modular way is that it's very clear
about where things are coming from.
Now, for those who really care about destructuring,
making your code shorter, there are ways to do it.
We're not going to cover it right now, because I do think using it out of
the box like this has its advantages for being declarative and easy to understand.
So, now that we save this, go ahead and take a look at how that looks.
And there we go, everything is showing up as expected.
Now, the other things we can possibly do with this is we want to go ahead and
practice getting the getters, right?
So, we were doing that on the home page, right here.
To go on the app page, we had the ability to, wait, no, home page is here.
We were looking at something called short user list.
Well, what we can do instead is actually take this part, and
we can shorten the code by saying, okay, we're going to take this calculation
that we've done, and we're going to go to the user store.
And inside of our getters, we're going to get a short user list, short user list.
And we can use an arrow function for this, where we'll get the state, and
it'll return state.userList, and we don't need the value.
And this is the equivalent of our computed property.
Now that we have this in here, we can go back over to our home page,
which is right here.
And we can actually now just remove this in its entirety.
And we can then say, instead of import userList,
we're actually going to import useUserStore.
There you go, it's autocompleted, fantastic.
constUserStore equal useUserStore, we were calling that.
And now that this is available to us, we can then say,
userStore.shortUserList, save.
So now we go back to the home, there we go, user home, there we go.
We have our short list, it's all kept in one place.
Now one last thing before we wrap this up is that we need to actually verify how
do we do actions, right?
And so there was a great question earlier regarding the fact that if we look at
userStore, you might be tempted to actually make this part some sort of
asynchronous functionality, right?
Like I want to fetch this, return it into this value.
But when it comes to setting up state and managing that with composables,
my recommendation for doing that is to always start with the initial empty
state, that's where that should start.
And then later on, when you're writing code, you'll have that,
oh, go ahead and overwrite and populate it.
But for now, always try to avoid the async stuff in here.
Keep that just to the standard data types.
However, what we can do, though, is inside of our actions,
this is where we can write that fetch functionality.
So where is that currently living right now?
My guess is it's on user page.
And sure enough, look at this, async function fetch users.
Let's just steal that entire thing away because it doesn't need to be here.
So let's grab that over into our userStore and drop that in.
Now, this current syntax won't work.
Why?
Because this is async function when you're defining it outside of an object.
So what we need to do is actually make fetch users an async function like this.
And then let me try to save it.
It'll format itself a little bit better, which is great.
And then there we go.
And then you can see we get the fetch here.
We get this response, and then we get the response.
But rather than just return it in this particular case,
because in this scenario, we're saying that this function is specific to the store.
Actually, you know what?
Take that back.
We're going to leave it like this.
I'll show you the two ways on why.
So now we have the fetch users here.
How are we going to use it?
Well, inside of our user page, we've gone ahead and we said, OK, we have the userStore.
So what can we do?
We can do userStore.fetch users.
So that should do the trick.
User.userList equals await userStore.fetch users.
Great.
Now we come here and refresh.
You'll see now that when we come over and refresh, everything is working still.
Now, there's also value in case that you're like, oh, well,
I don't want to have to manually fetch it.
I want to just, whenever this is called, go ahead and update this.
So an alternative model, there's no right or wrong.
It just depends on what your use case is.
If we go inside of our user page, rather than having to call userList and assign it,
what we could do, theoretically, is we just want to call userStore.fetch users.
That's all we want to do.
But if we do that, nothing's going to happen.
Why?
Because currently, inside of our function, all we're doing is actually running the userStore.
You see here, we're only returning the response.
We're actually not doing much with it.
So what we need to do instead is we need to refer to the userList.
And so, unlike the getters, which gets the state in an arrow function,
because the actions really do require the entire context of the app,
this is where this context comes back into play,
so that we can go this.userList equals response.
And so now, once we refresh that, you'll see everything appears as we expect.
And this is now, again, it's tightly coupled.
But at the same time, this might be OK in this particular instance,
because this is the global store.
So that's actually probably what we want to do.
When we fetch users, we want the entire global state to update.
So basically, I would say, if you're writing or composing your functionality
in this way, I think it does make sense to tightly couple.
In the event that fetch users has nothing to do with this,
and that's for whatever reason, it's a separate type of functionality,
that's where it might make sense as just a composable,
that you import into your store, that does something entirely separate,
that then you can better break it up and compose your code.
So we're at the tail end of all this.
Obviously, there is a lot more to cover,
as there's an entire world and ecosystem out there.
So some of the questions that have come up during this
include things like, what about things like design systems, component libraries?
Well, you're just in luck, because recently Vutify,
which is the official library for doing view components with material design,
that has actually been released.
So if you go to Vutify.js, I want to say is .org.
Nope.
Vutify.
.com, I messed up.
This is, I think, the most popular component library that the view ecosystem has,
when it comes to a really well-maintained team that helps to make sure everything's kept up to date.
As you can see here, they have wonderful documentation,
that if you come in here, you can actually take a look at the different components.
So earlier, I was showing someone the tables down here,
so you could take a look at something like a simple data table that automatically takes in data.
It looks beautiful, you can sort it without doing any additional work.
This is the kind of thing that you might want to check out,
if you don't have time to build your own design library and that kind of thing.
So Vutify, highly recommended checking that out.